Guide to the Robert M. Solow Papers, 1951-2011 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Robert M. Solow papers 1951-2011 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Solow, Robert M.
63.1 linear feet Extent: 45,300 Items
Nobel Prize-winning economist and economics professor emeritus at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. The Robert M. Solow Papers span the years 1951-2011 and document the full scope of his professional, scholarly, and academic work. The majority of the collection consists of correspondence (1960-2011) with students, colleagues, and other economists, and it includes his reviews of papers by other scholars, referee reports, letters of recommendation, articles written for the public, professional correspondence as well as policy recommendations. The papers also contain lecture notes for courses Solow taught at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (1972-1996); published papers by Solow on macroeconomics, growth theory, linear programming, and other topics (1950-2011); and files from economic, academic, and governmental organizations in which he served, including the American Economics Association and the Econometrics Society, and the Council of Economic Advisors to the White House. The collection is divided into the following series: Correspondence, Teaching Materials, Published Papers and Writings, Professional Service, and Audiovisual Materials.
RL.01239
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Robert M. Solow Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from 2007-2011.
Biographical Note
Robert M. Solow is an American economist whose early work focused on statistics and econometrics, but gradually shifted to employment (specifically the theory of unemployment) and growth policies, macroeconomics, and theory of capital. Most recently his work has been on targets of opportunity and a collaborative effort with Frank Hahn focusing on macro-theory. He is perhaps best known for his work on the Neo-classical Growth Model, also known as the Solow-Swan Growth Model (1956).
Along with Paul Samuelson, he made up the core of the Massachussetts Institute of Technology Economics Department as Institute Professor Emeritus for over forty years. He has held several governmental positions, including Senior Economist for the Council of Economic Advisors (1961-1962), and was a member of the President's Commission on Income Maintenance (1968-1970). He served as president for both the American Economics Association and the Econometric Society, and is a member of the National Academy of Sciences, a Fellow of the British Academy, and a former member of the National Science Board. He is currently serving as Foundation Fellow at the Russell Sage Foundation.
Chronology List
1923 Aug. 23 Born in Brooklyn, NY
1940 Attended Harvard College
1942-1945 Served in the U.S. Army (North Africa, Sicily, and Italy)
1945 Returned to Harvard
1945 Married Barbara Lewis
1945 Research assistant to Wassily Leontief under whom he produced the first set of capital-coefficients for the input-output model
1947 Received B.A. from Harvard
1949 Received M.A. from Harvard
1949 Accepted an Assistant Professorship in the Economics Department at M.I.T.
1949-1950 Fellowship year at Columbia University
1951 Received Ph.D. from Harvard
1953 von Neumann Growth Theory (work and development)
1956 Capital Theory (work and development)
1958 Linear Programming (work and development)
1960 Phillips Curve (work and development)
1961 Awarded the American Economic Association’s John Bates Clark Medal
1961-1962 Senior economist for the U.S. Council of Economic Advisors
1962-1968 Served as consultant for the U.S. Council of Economic Advisors
1964 President of the Econometric Society
1968 Vice President of American Economic Association
1968-1970 Member of the President’s Commission on Income Maintenance
1970 Vice President of the American Association for the Advancement of Science
1975-1981 Member of the Board of Federal Reserve Bank of Boston
1979 President of the American Economic Association
1987 Awarded the Nobel Prize in Economics for analysis of economic growth
1995 Retired from teaching at MIT
1999 Received National Medal of Science
2000 Co-founded the Cournot Centre for Economic Studies
2011 Received honorary degree in Doctor of Science from Tufts University
Collection Overview
The papers of Nobel Prize-winning economist Robert M. Solow span the years 1951-2011 and document his professional, scholarly, and academic work. The majority of the collection consists of voluminous files of correspondence (1960-2011) with students, colleagues, and other economists, and it includes his reviews of papers by other scholars, referee reports, letters of recommendation articles for the public, professional correspondence as well as policy recommendations. The papers also contain lecture notes for courses Solow taught at MIT (1972-1996); published papers by Solow on macroeconomics, growth theory, linear programming, and other topics (1950-2011); and files from economic, academic, and governmental organizations in which he served, including the American Economics Association, the National Bureau of Economic Research, and the Institute for Advanced Study at Princeton. The published papers series also contains notes and rough drafts on topics such as econometrics, employment (specifically the theory of unemployment) and growth policies, macroeconomics, and the theory of capital. There is also some material on the Neo-classical Growth Model, also known as the Solow-Swan Growth Model (1956).
The largest series in the collection, the Correspondence Series is subdivided into three groups: Chronological Correspondence, Alphabetical Correspondence, and Recommendations. The first two consist of correspondence from students, colleagues, and collaborators, with some responses from Solow included. The exchanges include economists such as Kenneth Arrow, Olivier Blanchard, Alan Blinder, Partha Dasgupta, Frank Hahn, Paul Samuelson, and James Tobin. The alphabetical correspondence dating from 1951-1976, is similar in content to the chronological correspondence but smaller in size; it also contains more pieces related to organizations and businesses. The Alphabetical Correspondence (Recommendations) dating from 1971-1986, is the smallest of the three and consists of requests for and the subsequent letters of recommendation from Solow for either students or professional economists.
The Teaching Materials Series houses the teaching materials generated from Solow’s MIT economics courses (spanning an approximate 30 years of his 40 year MIT career) as well as the notes and materials used for lectures given at other forums and institutions. These materials consist of reading lists, syllabi, outlines, exams, problem sets and their solutions, homework, waivers, attendance rosters, assignments, spiral notebooks of economic equations, and personal preparatory notes handwritten by Solow.
Nearly all of Solow’s major publications and co-publications (see bibliography for the few exceptions) are found in the Published Papers and Writings Series. These include his Ph.D. thesis, speeches, lectures, invited lectures, panel discussions, op-ed pieces, journal articles, brochures, pamphlets, reviews of his works and his responses to the reviews, Congressional testimony, and memorial tributes, as well as the rough drafts and notes for these documents.
The Professional Service Series includes varied documents associated with the groups Robert Solow was either a member of, held a position in, wrote pieces for, or supported. Files contain correspondence, meeting minutes, proposals, reports, publications, votes, elections, and financial reports. The largest organizations represented in this series are the American Economic Association and the Institute for Advanced Study at Princeton.
Four videos featuring Solow are collected in the Audio Visual Series. Materials date from 2003 to 2009. Within the series, one item is recorded on a VHS cassette and the rest are in DVD format.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Solow, Robert M.; Massachusetts Institute of Technology; American Economics Association; Princeton University. Institute for Advanced Study; National Bureau of Economic Research; Capital; Econometrics; Economists -- United States -- Correspondence; Economic development; Employment; Growth models; Macroeconomics; DVDs; Videocassettes
Detailed Description of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1960-2011, (70 boxes)
  The Correspondence Series is the largest in the collection and is subdivided into three subseries. The Chronological Correspondence, dating from 1960 to 2011, is the largest of the three. It contains many files of personal and professional correspondence, including students and academics requesting comments on their work; conference and sabbatical invitations; letters asking for advice on economic problems from bank and federal officials; Christmas cards; congratulatory letters following his Nobel Prize; curriculum vitae and recommendation requests; thank you letters; and many more items. The Alphabetical Correspondence, dating from 1951-1976, is similar to the chronological correspondence in content. The first two subseries include Solow's exchanges with economists such as George Akerlof, Kenneth Arrow, Jagdish Bhagwati, Olivier Blanchard, Alan Blinder, Partha Dasgupta, Avinash Dixit, Frank Hahn, Robert Hall, Janos Kornai, Assar Lindbeck, Donald McCloskey, Ian McDonald, Luigi Pasinetti, Paul Samuelson, Vernon Smith, George Stigler, and James Tobin. The two subseries also include correspondence with politicians, like Daniel P. Moynihan and Joseph Biden, and with foundations, like Alfred P. Sloan Foundation. The Alphabetical Correspondence (Recommendations), dating from 1971-1986, is the smallest of the three and is a compilation of requests for and the subsequent letters of recommendation for either students or professional economists searching for job positions and/or entry into graduate and post-graduate school. As noted above, letters of recommendation are also included in the subsection Chronological Correspondence. The Correspondence Series covers a wide range of topics related to the growth model, neo-classicism, Keynes and Keynesianism, the efficiency wage model, price expectations, the money-wage dynamics, environmental policies as well as the state of the U.S. economy, including the rising inflation of the 1970s. Given their breadth and their span in time, the exchanges with Partha Dasgupta and Frank Hahn give excellent overviews about Solow the economist as well as Solow the man.
  - Chronological Correspondence, 1960-1999
    Correspondence arranged by date. Notable economists or topics are mentioned below each year's entry. The final box in this series (107) is a half-size manuscript box.
    - 1960 (Box 1)
      Roy Harrod.
    - 1961 (Box 1)
      AER referee reports.
    - 1962 (Box 1)
      Bernard F. Haley, Paul T. Homan, Dan Hamberg, Bent Hansen.
    - 1963 (Box 1)
      Frank H. Hahn, Roy Harrod, Walter W. Heller, Samuel Hollander, comment on Georgescu-Roegen.
    - 1964 (Box 1)
      Bert G. Hickman, Roy Harrod.
    - 1965 (Box 1)
      Robert L. Heilbroner.
    - 1966 (Box 1)
      Ernst Helmstadter on refinement of the Harrod's model, Frank H. Hahn, George A. Hay.
    - 1967 (Box 1)
      Arnold C. Harberger, Exchanges with Frank H. Hahn on hiring Mirrlees, hiring Dixit, deciding about Econometrica Editorship.
    - 1968 Jan.-1968 Jun. (Box 2)
      Robert W. Fogel, Harry G. Johnsson, R.C.O. Matthews, Gyorgy Szakolczai, Robert K. Merton on institutiing a prize in social sciences. Suggestions for the structure of The Econometric Society.
    - 1968 Jun.-1968 Oct. (Box 2)
      Robert W. Fogel.
    - 1969 Jan.-1969 Aug. (Box 2)
      A note on microeconomic theory.
    - 1969 Sept.-1969 Dec. (Box 2)
      Karl Shell, correspondence with Frank H. Hahn on his view of Keynes and the Keynesian Revolution, Edwin Burmeister.
    - 1970 Jan.-1970 Aug., (1 of 2) (Box 2)
      A refined version of a note on microeconomic theory, Robert J. Gordon, David Gale, recommendation of Joeseph E. Stiglitz and Mark Killingsworth, James A Mirrlees, correspondence with Edwin Burmeister on capital and growth theory, comments on Robert L. Heilbroner's paper, Daniel Bell, correspondence with Robert Dorfman on Phillips curve.
    - 1970 Jan.-1970 Aug., (2 of 2) (Box 2)
      Malcolm S. Cohen, Franklin M. Fisher, Arthur M. Okun, comments on Robert E. Hall's paper on wages and unemployment.
    - 1970 Sept.-1970 Dec., (1 of 2) (Box 2)
      Lester G. Telser.
    - 1970 Sept.-1970 Dec., (2 of 2) (Box 2)
      Frank H. Hahn.
    - 1970 (Box 2)
      Correspondence with: Stanley Fischer, Assar Lindbeck, Paul W. McCracken, James A. Mirrlees, William Nordhaus, Arthur Okun, Joan Robinson, Amartya Sen, Joseph E. Stiglitz, Lester G. Telser, Christian von Wezsaecher. Recommendations for: Robert E. Hall, Joseph E. Stiglitz. Essay "Microeconomic Theory".
    - 1971 Jan.-1971 Mar. (Box 3)
      Charlie E. Ferguson, Christian Werner, NBER proposal on examining whether the fluctuations in the "utilization" of the capital stock are large enough to account for the short-run behavior of labor productivity, correspondence with John K. Cordy on the Solow growth model.
    - 1971 Apr.-1971 Aug. (Box 3)
      Correspondence with Herbert A. Simon and David Gale on growth model, correspondence with Fredric Raines on wage and price dynamics.
    - 1971 Sept.-1971 Oct., (1 of 2) (Box 3)
      Frederick Forscher.
    - 1971 Sept.-1971 Oct., (2 of 2) (Box 3)
      Arnold Collery, James A. Mirrlees.
    - 1971 Nov.-1971 Dec. (Box 3)
      Kazuo Sato,comments on J. Herbert Hollomon's propposal on transportation externalities.
    - 1972 Jan.-1972 Mar. (Box 3)
      Correspondence with Peter A. Diamond, James A. Mirrlees. Book proposal of Christopher Dougherty on capital and profit. Comment on Joan Robinson's Collected Papers.
    - 1972 Jan.-1972 Mar., (2 of 2) (Box 4)
      Peter E. de Janosi.
    - 1972 Apr.-1972 Aug. (Box 4)
      Comments on J. Borkaktoti's paper on Solow's growth model, correspondence with Paul Isenman on the problem of laissez-faire as a guide to the proper path of economic growth, correspondence with Alfred E. Kahn on productivity.
    - 1972 Sep.-1972 Dec., (1 of 3) (Box 4)
      Alan S. Blinder. A draft of a thank you speech for Aron Gordon. Letter to Robert F. Drinan in support of environmental and public transit ammendments to the Federal Aid to Highways Act.
    - 1972 Sep.-1972 Dec., (2 of 3) (Box 4)
      Emilio Casetti, correspondence with George J. Stigler on Becker's theory of marrige.
    - 1972 Sep.-1972 Dec., (3 of 3) (Box 4)
      Garet Hardin. Recommendations for Peter A. Diamond and Robert J. Gordon.
    - 1972 (Box 4)
      Short letters.
    - 1973 Jan.-1973 Feb., (1 of 2) (Box 4)
      Mark R. Killingsworth.
    - 1973 Jan.-1973 Feb., (2 of 2) (Box 4)
      Gordon C. Cameron, correspondence with Veniero Del Punta on the Cambridge debate, George A. Akerlof, correspondence with Peter Der Sarkisiam regarding Solow's article on pollution and its control.
    - 1973 Mar.-1973 Apr., (1 of 2) (Box 5)
      Correspondence with John Rawls on Ramsey's model.
    - 1973 Mar.-1973 Apr., (2 of 2) (Box 5)
      Edwin Burmeister, comments on Anwar Shaikh's paper on production function, correspondence with Edgar L. Feige on the paper on the effectiveness of the wage-price control experiment, comments on Edwin S. Mills' Note of New Urban Economics.
    - 1973 May.-1973 Aug., (1 of 2) (Box 5)
      Richard B. Hansen, a rejoinder to a comment on Solow's article 'Is the End of the World at Hand?', comments on Aldo Montesano's paper on the general theory of land demand and rent, Richard J. Zeckhauser.
    - 1973 May.-1973 Aug., (2 of 2) (Box 5)
      Partha Dasgupta.
    - 1973 Sep.-1973 Oct. (Box 5)
      Peter Diamond, William D. Nordhaus. Exchanges with Arthur L. Singer from Alfred P. Sloan Foundation on the possible economics program of the foundation. Letter of recommendation for Robert E. Lucas, Jr.
    - 1973 Nov.-1973 Dec., (1 of 3) (Box 5)
      Includes short letters, letters of recommendation.
    - 1973 Nov.-1973 Dec., (2 of 3) (Box 5)
      Armen A. Alchian, Peter Diamond. Letter of recommendation for Avinash K. Dixit. Report on Institute for Advanced Study by Landon Y. Junes.
    - 1973 Nov.-1973 Dec., (3 of 3) (Box 5)
      Letter from W.W. Rostow on counter-productive attacks on equilibrium theory by Kaldor and others. Letters of recommendation for Vernon L. Smith.
    - 1973, (1 of 2) (Box 6)
    - 1974 Jan.-1974 Mar., (1 of 3) (Box 6)
      Peter Diamond, Charlotte K. Stiglitz.
    - 1974 Jan.-1974 Mar., (2 of 3) (Box 6)
      Roger G. Kennedy, response to T.S. Saini on capital
    - 1974 Jan.-1974 Mar., (3 of 3) (Box 6)
      Letter to Geoffrey Hall on Solow's Ely Lecture. Harry G. Johnson arguing that theory should be accessible to people with lower abilities in mathematics. Letter to Assar Lindbeck on short time horizons of politicians. Memorandum on Economics Program of The Sloan Foundation.
    - 1974 Mar.-1974 Apr., (1 of 2) (Box 6)
      Daniel Bell, Yoshitsugu Kanemote, Solow's article titled "Energy Crisis and Environment".
    - 1974 Mar.-1974 Apr., (2 of 2) (Box 6)
      Murray Kemp.
    - 1974 May-1974 Dec., (1 of 4) (Box 6)
      Robert Eisner, Douglas Lee.
    - 1974 May-1974 Dec., (2 of 4) (Box 6)
      The Sloan Foundation. Letter from James Tobin to Walter W. Heller on discretionary economic policy. Letters of recommendation for Alan S. Blinder and James Heckman. Biographical Sketch (multiple versions).
    - 1974 May-1974 Dec., (3 of 4) (Box 7)
      Daniel Bell, correspondence with Robert Eisner on his article titled "Keynesian Revolution Reconsidered".
    - 1974 May-1974 Dec., (4 of 4) (Box 7)
      Robert J. Gordon.
    - 1974, (1 of 2) (Box 7)
    - 1974, (2 of 2) (Box 7)
    - 1975 Jan.-1975 May, (1 of 3) (Box 7)
      Robert J. Barro. Letter to Senator Hubert H. Humphrey in support of further monetary expansion. Econometric Society Ballot. Arthur Smithies, paper Interest Rate Policy and Inflation.
    - 1975 Jan.-1975 May, (2 of 3) (Box 7)
      Bruce Gunn, Kazuo Sato, Michael Spence.
    - 1975 Jan.-1975 May, (3 of 3) (Box 7)
      Irving Kristol, a letter to editor of New York Times on stagflation by R.A. Gordon, Lawrence Klein, Franco Modigliani, Paul Samuelson, Robert Solow, Paul Taubman and James Tobin.
    - 1975 Sept.-1975 Dec., (1 of 5) (Box 7)
      Bertil Ohlin. Correspondence with Benjamin Higgins in support of research on central planning. Financial difficulties of The Econometric Society. Paper for popular audience "A Guide to Inflation".
    - 1975 Sept.-1975 Dec., (2 of 5) (Box 7)
      Robert Clower.
    - 1975 Sept.-1975 Dec., (3 of 5) (Box 8)
      Kazuo Sato, Paul Starr.
    - 1975 Sept.-1975 Dec., (4 of 5) (Box 8)
      Review Committee of Institute for Advanced Study, the letter of resignation of the Director of IAS, Carl Kaysen.
    - 1975 Sept.-1975 Dec., (5 of 5) (Box 8)
      S. Fred Singer.
    - 1975, (1 of 2) (Box 8)
    - 1975, (2 of 2) (Box 8)
    - 1976 Jan.-1976 Feb. (Box 8)
      Arthur F. Burns, R.A. Gordon, Eastern Economics Journal, Embassy of Israel, Harry G. Johnson, C.P. Kindleberger, Alfred P. Sloan Foundation, George Stigler, James Tobin,.
    - 1976 Feb.-1976 Mar. (Box 8)
      The Institute for Advanced Study.
    - 1976 Mar. (Box 8)
      Correspondence with George Eads on material shortage issues, comments on Heal's "The Influence of Interest Rates on Resource Prices".
    - 1976 (Box 8)
      Minutes for the meeting of the Review Committee of the Board of Trustees, the Institute for Advanced Study.
    - 1976 Apr.-1976 May (Box 9)
      The Institute for Advanced Study, Ashby McCown.
    - 1976 Aug.-1976 Sep. (Box 9)
      Avinash Dixit, F.H. Hahn, Jacob Marshak, Stephen L. Near (U.S. House of Representatives), Mancur Olson.
    - 1976 Oct.-1976 Nov. (Box 9)
      William J. Baumol, Partha Dasgupta, Gerard Debreu, Peter A. Diamond, Robert T. Hall. Letter of recommendation for Paul Krugman.
    - 1976 Nov.-1976 Dec. (Box 9)
      Peter Diamond, Stephen Allen, George Akerlof.
    - 1977 Jan.-1977 Feb. (Box 9)
      Arthur Burns, James Tobin. Tenure evaluation of Rudiger Dornbusch.
    - 1977 Mar.-1977 Apr. (Box 9)
      H.O. Stekler, Partha Dasgupta.
    - 1977 May.-1977 Jul. (Box 9)
      Bent Hansen, George R. Walker.
    - 1977 Aug.-1977 Oct. (Box 9)
      Daniel M. Hausman.
    - 1977 Oct.-1977 Dec. (Box 9)
      A draft of "The Public Letter on Tax Incentives for Restraining Wage/Price Inflation", James Tobin, Peter Berck, Ronald Grieson.
    - 1978 Jan. (Box 10)
      Arthur F. Burns, Guillermo Calvo.
    - 1978 Feb.-1978 Mar. (Box 10)
      Robert J. Gordon, Herschel I. Grossman. Referee letter for Alfred P. Sloan Foundation on proposal from Law and Economics Center. Public Letter on Tax Incentives for Restraining Inflation.
    - 1978 Apr.-1978 May (Box 10)
      Robert M. Unger, Brian Hiller.
    - 1978 Jun.-1978 Nov. (Box 10)
      Correspondence with Martin N. Baily on capital utilization and short-run productivity.
    - 1978 Oct.-1978 Nov. (Box 10)
      Comments on Axel Leijonhufvud's paper on Wicksell.
    - 1978 Dec. (Box 10)
      Philip Saunders, Jr.
    - 1979 Jan.-1979 Feb. (Box 10)
      Edwin S. Mills, Allan G. Shemman on inflation.
    - 1979 Mar.-1979 Apr. (Box 10)
      Bruce Hannon.
    - 1979 Apr.-1979 Jun. (Box 10)
      John E. Roemer.
    - 1979 May.-1979 Jul. (Box 11)
      Drafts of an article titled "Toward Realism about Inflation", Paul Davidson.
    - 1979 Aug. (Box 11)
      John Snell.
    - 1979 Aug.-1979 Sep. (Box 11)
      Mo-huan Hsing, Steven Hayworth.
    - 1979 Oct. (Box 11)
      George Akerlof.
    - 1979 Nov.-1979 Dec. (Box 11)
      Correspondence with William A. Darity on Keynes and Unemployment, correspondence with Robert Hall on rational expectations.
    - 1980 Jan. (Box 11)
    - 1980 Feb. (Box 11)
      Robert J. Gordon, Julius Margolis.
    - 1980 Mar. (Box 11)
      John S. Pettengill.
    - 1980 Apr. (Box 11)
      Corinne S. Schelling, Robert J. Gordon.
    - 1980 May (Box 11)
      Mo-huan Hsing, Heidi I. Hartman, correspondence with John Hicks on labor market.
    - 1980 May.-1980 Aug. (Box 12)
      Letter on a collaborative project with Ian McDonald.
    - 1980 Sep. (Box 12)
      George J. Stigler. Letter from Ray C. Fair on econometrics of uncertainty.
    - 1980 Oct. (Box 12)
      Vernon W. Rutton's reply on growth.
    - 1980 Nov.-1980 Dec. (Box 12)
      Richard Stone, Paul A. Volcker.
    - 1981 Jan. (Box 12)
      Paul A. David.
    - 1980 May (Box 11)
    - 1980 May.-1980 Aug. (Box 12)
    - 1980 Sep. (Box 12)
    - 1980 Oct. (Box 12)
    - 1980 Nov.-1980 Dec. (Box 12)
    - 1981 Jan. (Box 12)
    - 1981 Feb. (Box 12)
      Alfred P. Sloan Foundation.
    - 1981 Mar. (Box 12)
      Herschel I. Grossman.
    - 1981 Apr. (Box 12)
      C. Alan Garner
    - 1981 Jun.-1981 Aug. (Box 12)
      Reply to Edward P. Lazear on labor market.
    - 1981 Sep. (Box 12)
      Kosta Tsipis.
    - 1981 Oct. (Box 12)